anyways so you're always in in a
situation and then this is occurs across
multiple levels of analysis because I
could say well winner you in the garden
and one answer could be well when you're
in a beautiful house or in a beautiful
hotel or in a well-functioning
institution or in a city that's working
but I can also say you're in a garden
when you're conception of the world is
sufficient that when you enact it it
allows the world to be fruitful
that's a garden too right because so
your internal psychological structure
the conceptions that you use first of
all there are obviously analogous to
culture but they're also analogous to a
garden in that way and light culture
they can be disrupted so you know what
it's like people they say this all the
time I wish that hadn't happened and
what they mean by that is geez I was in
a pretty good place before that event
occurred you know and a big moral error
can really do that to you you know you
do something that you really think is
stupid and you know you you're just
shattered really
sometimes shattered enough to develop
post-traumatic stress disorder so you
can't get rid of the snakes that's the
first idea in the story well then the
issue is well what do you do with the
stakes well God basically told even Adam
not well he didn't really tell them not
to interact with the snakes and he put a
snake in there I think it's partly
because in a sense it's not possible to
create a garden without having a snake
in it because you can't keep everything
out it's not possible okay so the snake
comes along and it says well if you do
this thing that god forbade a lot of
wonderful things will happen well this
is where it gets exhibited gets
extraordinarily complicated you know
let me finish that this part of the
story and then we'll go back the serpent
said unto the woman ye shall not surely
die for God knows that in the day you
eat thereof then your eyes will be
opened and you will be as God's knowing
good and evil okay so what can we
conclude from that well the first thing
is is that their eyes were closed
because if they weren't closed and how
could they be opened and the second
thing is they didn't know the difference
between good and evil okay so that
explains the whole ashame naked and not
ashamed issue because if your eyes are
closed well that's irrelevant and if you
know if there's no moral knowledge
there's obviously no shame so what's
happening here is that there's a very
profound distinction being made between
the before fruit eating state of being
in the after fruit eating state of being
or the before fruit eating and snake
interacting mode of being and the after
fruit eating and snake interacting mode
of being and I think it's reasonable to
think of that on a historical timeline
you know that that is one of the major
those are two of the major forces that
shaped our evolutionary history and the
idea that things were different before
that and after that is a perfectly
reasonable presupposition something put
us on the path to very very rapid
cortical development vision is certainly
one of those factors so and the fruit
eating element well that's where we have
color vision so it isn't obvious exactly
what that did but it did a lot of things
so and then the next thing is well
there's no moral knowledge now that's
interesting because it implies that
there's some tight link between having
your eyes closed and not having moral
knowledge so to have your eyes closed is
to not to be able to see so there's a
kind of unconsciousness about it and
when the woman saw that the tree was
good for food and that was pleasant to
the eyes and a tree to be desired to
make one wise she took of the fruit
thereof and did eat and gave also unto
her husband with her and he did eat
and the eyes of both of them were opened
and they knew they were naked and they
sewed fig leaves together and made
themselves aprons okay so that's quite
an interesting sequence of events so
they're tempted by this thing that's
subtle and dangerous and the consequence
of the temptation is the ingestion of
something the incorporation of something
with transformative properties and the
transformation is profound what happens
is they open their eyes well that's
coming to consciousness that's exactly
what that is now when a kitten opens its
eyes it finally enters the world you
know so people had their eyes closed
before this event well so they weren't
they weren't conscious in the same way
and that would account for the unity of
experience they're not separated from
they're not separate beings on the
ground of existence that's one way of
thinking but they have the same kind of
life as animals do you know they're
they're just unconscious or at least non
self conscious entities of nature
there's no nakedness there's no
knowledge of good and evil I mean do you
you don't blame a lion for eating it for
reading a sheep well they did this thing
yeah they used to eat sheep in the
Middle East right you don't think that's
an evil they don't think of the lion as
evil
you just think that that's what Lions do
now someone comes along and steals your
sheep well that's a whole different
issue all of a sudden there's a moral
issue that's overlaid upon that and you
say well you might say well why is all
of a sudden there a moral issue and then
the answer to that would be well the
person either does know the difference
between good and bad or should know it
you know and if he says well I'm just
acting like a lion that's just it's just
not going to no one's going to accept
that as an excuse and the reason for
that is there's a basic assumption that
there's something that you know that
lions don't and that why well it's
because your eyes are open in a
different way okay well that seems to be
reasonable so they open their eyes and
bang they know they're naked now that's
an interesting juxtaposition okay so
let's say you develop a higher form of
consciousness and that makes you
self-conscious so there's two things
happening here there's an elevation of
consciousness but out of that spraying
self-consciousness
and then you got to think what a
self-consciousness mean exactly
well because you're not fully
self-conscious and the reason you're not
fully self-consciousness because you
don't know everything about yourself
right so you're you're ignorant of a lot
of your own being but there's a lot of
you're being you're not ignorant about
well eh you can identify yourself as an
individual so you've got the identify
yourself in the mirror trick down which
is kind of a standard trick for animal
self-consciousness but that's only the
beginning it's the bare beginnings of
self-consciousness if you're so if
you're self-conscious you know where
your boundaries are because what's
inside the boundary is you and what's
outside isn't you but then there's other
boundaries that you have there's a
temporal boundary there's there's the
time when you weren't and there's the
time when you won't be and so there's a
boundary in space but there's about a
boundary in time and that means that as
soon as you become self conscious you
know that you're going to die and so
that's the tight link between the fruit
of the tree of knowledge of good and
evil and the and death in the Old
Testament or in the Genesis story so and
you might say while you were going to
die before and fair enough but there's a
big difference between the death the
death of a self conscious entity and
death in the one case it's a natural
process that know that that's natural
death let's say and the other one except
it's a catastrophe of being for the self
conscious individual you know and so the
other thing that happens is in the
Genesis story that that discovery is
portrayed as a permanent rift in the
structure of being that's why it's such
a deep sin it's like all of a sudden
everything is different and it will
never be the same again no matter what
happens you know when you might say well
obviously God was an enemy of higher
consciousness it's like well there's
lots of interpretations of Genesis that
took exactly that stat said well God was
an enemy of higher self higher
consciousness he wanted things to remain
in an unconscious paradise and that it
was human unwillingness to behave and
curiosity that God has sent to the
problem that were in and it's actually
actually a catastrophe you know and then
other people who were sort of hired that
had more say admiration for the
illumination and self-consciousness
element said that the thing that tempted
human beings was a greater God than the
God that originally did the creation
that was a Gnostic idea you know so the
serpent there becomes a an agent of
Revelation in a sense you know but
anyways this they've laid out the
problem this is the problems all of a
sudden people woke up and when they woke
up they noticed who they were and they
weren't happy about it so what do they
notice they're naked okay well so what
well you know you see so what instantly
because the first thing they do is make
fig leaves they make a you know clothing
out of fig leaves and cover themselves
up well you know that's that's culture
and you think well what's good what is
the utility of culture well that's easy
culture is the barrier between us and
and our own nakedness it's the barrier
between our nakedness and the natural
world it's like why do you put on
clothes so you don't freeze to death you
know so that you're not as easily
attacked it's like as soon as you know
you're naked and vulnerable and you're
self-conscious you extend yourself
across time you've discovered time you
know that not only are you vulnerable
now but you're going to be vulnerable in
the future it's or your children and
their children it's like the whole
nature of being it's like you've added a
dimension to the nature of being you've
added time to it and it's a radical
transformation you might say well that's
good because lions don't eat you as
often it's like yeah the zebras don't
seem that upset on plains of the
Serengeti when the Lions are around
one's going to pick one off now and then
but the lion the zebras aren't running
around you know with anxiety disorders
popping valium all the time because the
Lions are there but would that's not the
case with human beings we see a line and
we think oh yeah some at some point that
line is going to want to eat one of us
and so and lions in general will do that
so not only do we have to solve the
problem of that lion right now we have
to solve the problem of all lions for
all time which we actually seem to be
doing a very good job of know as soon
there won't be any of them but you know
so that sort of thing can get out of
hand but but you get the point so ok so
they they sewed fig leaves together and
they made the
selves aprons so you know the sexual
element of it too is I think also that
the reason sexuality is tied in this so
tightly is because the most sexual parts
of a human being are also the parts that
are the most vulnerable so though it's
not only you know vulnerability to
judgment and vulnerability to
exploitation which is a huge deal
especially in the case of women but it's
also the fact that just from a purely
physical perspective those are the most
delicate tissues and so the fact that
they're fully exposed is really a big
problem so okay so now they're naked
they got aprons on it's like an you know
you they're not in unconscious paradise
anymore so then what happens and they
heard the voice of the Lord God walking
in the garden in the cool of the day and
Adam and his wife hid themselves from
the presence of the Lord God amongst the
trees of the garden I can't imagine how
you could possibly pack more meaning
into two sentences you know it's you can
tell people have been at this for like
twenty five thousand years because see
what happens here is that there's an
idea to begin with that there's a
complete unity between God and his
creation
let's say so that there's the natural
order is undisturbed and all of a sudden
that's fractured and so what happens is
that human beings are divorced from the
divinity and it's and not only are they
divorced from it they're unwilling to
expose themselves to it so so think
about think about this I will take a
take a sidestep for a minute
you might say well imagine that you
could exist in a manner that was Nile
and perfect the question might be well
what would stop you from doing it well
one thing might be that you couldn't
envision something as useless as you are
actually managing that you know so you
know if you think about that what stands
in the road of people as obstacles to
their full self-realization the easiest
way to encapsulate that is that they
view themselves as inadequate now
there's other things as well they don't
want to take the responsibility and so
forth but you know it's very difficult
to heed a divine call let's say when
you're stuck in this little ratty
contraption that is prone to disease and
and prone to shame and prone to age and
prone to death and it's like how can you
continue in some divine manner when
you've come to the realization that
there you are
you know and people certainly people
derive the conclusion fairly frequently
that they're so appalling that it would
be better if they were obliterated along
with everyone else it's not as if the
realization of the nature of our own
physical belly being was something that
freed people up to be courageous you
know it was quite the reverse although I
think people can still be courageous in
front of it in spite of it but it's
definitely in spite of it you know all
the classic definitions of true courage
aren't that you're not afraid it's that
you're afraid but you do it anyways it's
like well you that fear is its and shame
is an integral part of you as soon as
you realize that you're vulnerable to
social evaluation and natural
degeneration you're stuck with it and so
then bang you're divorced from your
divine mode of being will say partly at
least because you're just afraid to
manifest it so anyways that's what
happens so Adam and Eve hide from God
now that seems to be really
counterproductive because you might
think that if they didn't hide from God
then there wouldn't be a problem they
could be naked and no problem but that
isn't what happens and the Lord God
calls unto adamant says unto Him where
art where are you and Adam says I heard
your voice in the garden so there's a
call there and I was afraid because I
was naked well that pretty much explains
it and I hid
so okay and God said who told you that
you were naked have you eaten of the
tree whereof I commanded thee that thou
shouldn't sure does not eat who told
thee that thou was naked I believe women
told men that I think that's a very
accurate summation of the relationship
between men and women well we develop
consciousness across the span of
evolutionary history and I believe it
for a couple of reasons number one
sexual selection is a huge factor in in
what created human beings and women
primarily do the selection they're the
bottleneck and they're the bottleneck
because women can't have that many
offspring they can only have a few so
that makes them the bottleneck by
definition and women are so choosy about
men that twice as many women have
children as men okay so what that means
is on average means that I know it's
kind of hard to understand but imagine
every single woman has one child and
then imagine half the men have zero and
half of them have two okay that's the
case so statistically speaking half man
half of all men were right offs now it's
actually worse than that
because some men have so many offspring
that is not even funny you know so that
cuts it you know it cuts the number of
successful men down by many so women are
a bottleneck and they do judge men and
rightly so and they judge them according
to their insufficiency and that is what
makes men self-conscious obviously and
it's the thing that makes them more
self-conscious than anything else now to
men's credit let me tell you about the
bowerbirds okay so bowerbirds they're
very cool they live on the ground and
the male's make these incredibly first
of all they leave a nest that's sort of
like a hammock it's real soft and they
hang that into tree and then they sweep
out their front yard and then they
decorate it with bits of like the blue
leaves are over here and then there's
some red leaves here there's a nice
display of green here maybe there's some
glass there it's like this little
artwork you know and the bower birds
have these more or less in a row say in
the same territory and then the females
come hopping along and they take a look
at this thing and if they like it well
then they're willing to become a little
friendly with that particular bowerbird
and if they don't they fly away well so
if the male bowerbird has three female
visitors and nothing pans out then he
you know he has a little fit and erases
his old creation then he has to do
another one
and so like he just have to think about
that for 15 minutes and it pretty much
explains human beings it's like you know
men one response that man could have had
was just to go hide in a shell and some
of them do that that is absolutely a
common response and to never come out
and spend the rest of the lives playing
video games in the basement and eating
Cheetos you know but then you know the
other response is well I better
transform myself into something that
isn't going to produce that response and
that's a central part of that's a
central part of male motivation it's a
central element of male motivation so if
you're ever wondering why men are the
way they are that real answer to that is
because that's how they evolved to
impress women so because obviously if
that wouldn't have happened given that
sexual selection is such a powerful
selecting force among human beings well
it wouldn't have worked out so men women
did make men self-conscious you know
when it's more than that - because you
could see a positive feedback loop
emerging as we got more cognitively
sophisticated you know and you could
think of that maybe that was an arms
race between men women and snakes
something like that you know as we got
more cognitively sophisticated one of
the prices we paid for that was that our
head expanded and one of the prices
women paid for that was that childbirth
became increasingly difficult and the
babies kept getting born younger and so
that meant that women became more as we
became more cognitively able
paradoxically women became more
vulnerable at certain key points of
their lives because they had
increasingly fragile babies now how do
women deal with that well I think they
shamed men into becoming caregivers of
children because how else would it have
happened like the typical MIT mammal
male doesn't hang around provisioning
the
litter you know in fact some of the
males will eat the Cubs you don't want
to blow up male black bear around wolves
are son exception to this you know there
are animals that
an exception it happens in other species
other than human beings but human beings
have this incredibly long period of
dependence that also requires a
relationship for that relationship to
the remain intact there has to be a fair
bit of integrity in the communication
between the partners so there's a real
moral demand there as well so anyways
Adam doesn't show himself here as a
particularly courageous individual
because which i think is quite comical
when god says hope who told you that you
were naked had you know have you eaten
of that tree which I told you not to the
man says the woman ha who you gave to me
she gave me the tree of the tree and I
did eat which is like doesn't say much
for his moral territory because he'll
answer out the first chance he gets so
which I also think isn't like the comedy
of that is underrated in this story
that's a very funny sequence of events
so and so the God talks to the woman who
says well what's this that you did and
the woman said well the serpent it was
the Serpent's fault the serpent beguiled
me and I did eat let me show you up I
think I've showed you this picture
before but it's such a crazily cool
picture I want to show it to you again
okay well for whatever reason this disk
doesn't seem to be working so I'll tell
you about the picture instead it's a
very common representation in Christian
iconography and what it basically shows
is that Mary is holding up this infant
you know up off the ground she's got her
foot on a snake or lizard it's like well
it doesn't take a biological genius to
figure out what that means it means like
the good mother keeps the baby away from
predatory reptiles you know and so you
can see that as part of this feedback
loop that develops so there's predation
it's particularly focused on women and
children which is exactly what it would
be focused on so and then in order for
that to not be to not be catastrophic
then the women are appealing to the men
for protection and that starts to
increase because the women get more
vulnerable as we get smarter and the
babies get smaller and so there's this
triadic positive feedback loop that
occurs that wraps up brain development
and we need it there has to be a reason
for the brain development it's this
called a Baldwin effect by the way in
biology the Baldwin effect is where
something happens to produce an outcome
something biological happens that
produces a cultural outcome that
increases the probability that that
biological adaptation will serve
sickness so for example beavers cut down
trees so and what that means is that the
beavers that are more adapted to aquatic
environments do better so as the beavers
get more adapted to aquatic environments
and cutting down trees they cut down
more trees and make more aquatic
environments and so the thing spins
until you get a animal that's really
really well adapted to doing precisely
that well something happened to blow our
cortex up in very very short order and
it was shorter you know it was so short
that the human female pelvic structure
could barely keep up which is why birth
is so rough and why so many children
died in childbirth I mean it doesn't
have much anymore but God it used to
happen a lot you know before the middle
of the 20th century women were dying in
childbirth
all the time plus it's extraordinarily
difficult so even though the baby is
born premature for all intents and
purposes it's still hell and the reason
for that is the head is so big and it's
even compressible because the baby's
head isn't fully formed when it's born
bones have gaps in them so the baby's
head
and like like mad visibly so so the
women says well it was the Serpent's
fault so you know and you could almost
you could also say this ties into the
issue of woman induced
self-consciousness among men it's like
if the woman's primary primary problem
is predation you know for her and the
infant because of her you know being
burdened with the infants and the
infant's complete and absolute inability
to defend itself then it's going to
drive the probability that she's going
to select someone for a partner who can
get rid of the damn snakes and then you
know you see that echoed over and over
and human iPhoneography it's like the
hero is the person who confronts the
dragon okay well what do you do when you
confront a dragon you get the girl
that's the first thing but more
importantly you get something of value
and that's a real transmutation it's so
interesting because what happened was
not only did we figure out how to defend
ourselves against predators we figured
out that going after them voluntarily
was unbelievably useful because you
might ask what the hell transformed you
know frugivores and into carnivores it's
a you know chimps will eat and they do
hunt they will eat monkeys but they
primarily live on leaves which is
pointless you know because the leaves
have no calories whatsoever well human
beings like we got transformed we are
primarily fruit eaters and we turned
into hunters and we're thin and fast
which is very unlike a chimpanzee
so not only where women selecting men
who were able and willing to protect
themselves against predators but that
you know got translated even farther
into selection for for partners who
would go out partly to protect and
partly also to hunt to bring something
back so it always Perdita knits a pretty
smart arrangement all things considered
but the problem is you know one of the
prices that women pay for that is that
they're partly selecting for male
aggression you know because the males
aren't going to go up they're not going
to be able to do that sort of thing
unless they're tough and they're not
going to go out and do it unless there
relatively fearless so you know and then
you end up with a you got this weird
balance between needing a semi predator
and needing someone who's going to be
able to integrate themselves into the
household so that's the beauty and the
beast' thing as far as I can tell so
okay so the look god says to the serpent
because you've done this you're cursed
above all cattle cattle were generally
the animals and above every beast of the
field upon thy belly you will go and
dust you will eat all the days of your
life okay so the Serpent's got your
problem there and interesting to find
out exactly why those damn things lost
their legs because you know that snakes
snake lizards aren't snakes that grew
legs snakes are lizards that lost their
legs the question is why did the hell
did they lose their legs like what was
it about the specifics of their
environment and their diet and their
locale that meant that legless movement
was better well they're sneakier you
know they can slither through the grass
they can climb trees too although
Gowanus do that but I don't know enough
about snakes to know exactly why it was
that they lost their legs but be
interesting to find out and unto the
woman and I'll put enmity between though
and the woman and between hers by seed
and her seed it shall bruise thy head
and thou shalt bruise his heel okay so
it's just another representation of the
fact that there's going to be enmity
between human beings and predatory will
say predatory reptiles unto the woman he
said I will greatly multiply thy sorrow
and thy conception that's not hard to
figure out in sorrow shalt thou bring
forth children and thy desire shall be
to thy husband and he shall rule over
thee notice that doesn't say should it
just says she'll and that's not the same
thing at all remember this is a curse
it's not a it's not a proposition about
how the world should be optimally
structured it's far different than that
it says look there's been a sequence of
events and this is going to be the
outcome
childbirth is going to be hell it's
going to be really difficult to raise
children and you're going to be subject
to the oppression of men it's like yeah
well that's definitely what happened and
then Dante atomy says because you listen
to your wife and ate of the tree which I
told you not to
the grounds cursed for your sake you'll
eat it in sorrow all the days of your
life it'll bring up thorns and thistles
and you'll eat the herb of the field so
that's the introduction of the necessity
of agriculture right you're no longer
living in a garden where things are just
growing for free you're out there like
digging with the stick and planting
things which is work you know when you
think well do animals work and answer
that is no human beings work they answer
that is yes why do human beings work how
about because we discovered time right
because work means why do you work while
you work for the future obviously and
you don't have the future unless you
discover time and you don't care about
the future unless you know you're
vulnerable so these things are tangled
together so the cost of
self-consciousness is that work life
becomes work like life become suffering
and work so doesn't necessarily seem
like a particularly good deal in the
sweat of valley face you shall eat bread
until you return to the ground for out
of it you were taken for your dust and
unto dust you'll return and Adam called
his wife's name Eve because she was the
mother of all living and add unto Adam
also and to his wife did the Lord God
make coats of skins and clothed them so
okay well you know that's certainly part
of the origin of clothing especially in
the colder climes right it's like you
get the animal maybe it's a predator and
you wear it too and to begin with we
lived inside of them you know so I
suspect although I don't know this for
sure although I know it fairly well the
earliest dwellings were mammoth skins
with mammoth bone poles and you can see
see how that might have come about right
because you're out there hunting a
mammoth maybe you're living in a cave or
whatever the hell people live or maybe
you made something out of you know grass
Heidi and I don't know what the
Paleolithic people were living in but it
starts to get cold maybe the ice age
starts creeping up right and so you stab
yourself a nice mammoth and a storm
comes up what are you going to do
well you've skinned it out at least in
principle so you could carry the meat
home the logical thing to do is to get
the hell underneath the skin and after a
day or two in a storm underneath a
rotting mammoth skin you might think
well wouldn't be a bad idea to like do
something to the skin so that it's no
quite as intolerable to live under as it
might be if that's a tent like a tent is
skinned with bones you know and then the
movement from that to this is well it's
a matter of degree rather than kind so
and then the Lord God sent the man and
woman or the Lord God says Behold the
man is become as one of us to know good
and evil so that's the sign of divinity
to know good and evil to have a moral
sense and now lest he put forth his hand
and take also of the tree of life and
eat and live forever therefore the Lord
God sent him forth from the Garden of
Eden to till the ground from whence he
was taken so he drove out the man and he
placed at the east of the Garden of Eden
cherubims and a flaming sword which
turned every way to keep the way of the
Tree of Life well the last part of
that's very difficult to understand you
know the tree of life issue so the idea
there is that there's there's at least
in principle a substance capable of what
of conferring immortality but we don't
have access to that and so and you know
part of the return to Eden which is also
the movement towards heaven which is
also the perfection of life is to defeat
death obviously and to find the elixir
of immortality which by the way was the
goal of the entire alchemical pursuit
and that's what turned into science and
well what's the goal of science well
it's to make us healthy wealthy and live
you know conceivably forever so you know
it's not like people aren't continually
trying to get the fruit of the tree of
life now there's a lot more to it than
that the ending of that but but what you
have there is the the expulsion of human
beings from an unconscious paradise into
history and that's exactly how the Bible
is structured like what happens is
there's these stories in Genesis that
are very very old
there's the these stories there's the
story of Cain and Abel there's the story
of Babel of the Tower of Babel there's
the story of Noah then roughly speaking
although it happens a bit with Noah
history starts because then when you get
past that you get to the post-flood
period
like the pre-flood period is so back in
prehistory that it's all archaic
mythology and the post-flood period
which basically starts with Abraham
starts to become a history of the
culture of Israel so it's actually it's
actually literally it's the history of a
culture instead of the mythologies ation
of the you know radical prehistory of
the past so you know I think I'll also
just tell you briefly the Cain and Abel
story because we're there we might as
well do it and this is this story is
roughly speaking 12 sentences long so
okay so adamant and he have a child Cain
and AD and Eve says I have gotten a man
from the Lord and again she bought her
his brother Abel and Abel was a keeper
of sheep but Cain was a tiller of the
ground so there's some antagonism here
between the the Shepherds and the
farmers and that's like there's always
antagonism between shepherds and farmers
because the Shepherd's want the sheep to
graze all over the place and the farmers
want the shape to stay the hell out of
the out of the fields you know and that
was all played out again in the American
West there was huge you know conflict
between the farmers and the ranchers for
exactly the same reason so and it came
in process of time it came to pass that
Cain brought of the fruit of the ground
an offering unto the Lord all right so
this is a strange thing so we've already
talked about the discovery of time and
the necessity for work okay so you know
we don't exactly know how people
conceptualized of those ideas it wasn't
like they were cavemen or all sitting
around the fire one day and they said
hey you know what I just discovered
tomorrow we should do something about
that we should get to work it was
thought only knows how that happened it
came out of the inarticulate biological
substructure that is our past and
started to manifest itself god only
knows in imaginative ideas but one of
those imaginative ideas is the idea of
the sacrifice you know it's the
conceptualization of God the Father as
that which extends across time and
judges then you make sacrificial
offerings to that which
which could be of your labor this is of
the fruits of your labor but the
difference is trivial it's like look
what I've done is this good enough for
you and believe me you guys are asking
that question all the time it's like
it's just non-stop is this good enough
is this good enough is this sacrifice
enough you know and what are you hoping
for while you're hoping for the
blessings of well I would say for all
intents and purposes you're hoping for
the blessings of God the Father now you
might think about it pure cultural terms
that's fine from a psychological
perspective it hardly makes any
difference at all the point is is that
to conceptualize culture across time as
a judgmental male is a really smart idea
it's a really really smart idea so and
then it's a judgmental male that you
have to make offerings to it's like yeah
yeah that's that's pretty much exactly
right okay so that's what's happening
and so people are acting this out you
have to make sacrifices Cain brings some
you know vegetables and fruit and and
Abel brings not he brings like some
lambs and these are as a high quality
Lambs right there the choice cuts and we
know that partly because the first linge
of the flock so that's the firstborn say
lambs there there they had a reputation
as the most valuable and partly because
the firstborn son was the most valuable
it's the same kind of idea and there's a
reason the firstborn son was most
valuable and part of the reason is is
that unless you give all your land to
one of your children by 12 generations
all of your offspring are living on
something the size of a postage stamp
and they're all starving to death
so it's unfair in a sense that it only
goes to the firstborn son but if it's an
agricultural community there's no better
solution and then at least you can tell
your second born son like well yeah
you're a fine guy and you know it would
be wonderful if you could get something
but you don't get it and it's not your
fault it's not my fault either it's just
that's just the rule and so that's a
good deal for everybody you know you
don't get the farm you have to go make
your own way but at least there's no
enmity associated with it necessarily
so anyways Cain makes this offering that
looks like it's a Vicryl
and God is happy about that and the Lord
had respect unto Abel and to is offering
now the book the story makes this
ambiguous a you can kind of guess that
the reason that Abel gets away with it
is because well a he's bringing meat
rather than vegetables okay so that's
higher-quality
much more much more nutrient-dense it's
much higher quality offering of food and
then it's also of the meat it's the
highest quality and so and then the next
thing that happens is it's acceptable to
God so you know it might be that Abel
just got it right and God was happy or
maybe God's happy about Abel for some
completely arbitrary reason it actually
doesn't matter at all you get value out
of both interpretations I mean I would
say to err on the safe side that
offering the most valuable things is
probably your best bet but there's an
art there's an some respect for the
arbitrary nature of God here too you
can't exactly be sure why he's not happy
with Cain
so anyways doesn't matter until Canaan
is offering he had not respect and Cain
was very wroth angry that is and his
countenance fall so like this is a
permanent disappointment for him he's
angry resentful unhappy miserable all of
those things he's failing that's what it
says
fundamentally like if God isn't pleased
by his offerings what happens is he's
failing and this makes him very angry
and then the Lord says what what's up
with you why are you angry and why is
your face fallen the way it has and he
says more than this is where it gets it
seems the story seems to reveal that
this actually has something to do with
Cain rather than something to do with
God so God says if you do well won't you
be accepted well that implies he wasn't
doing well and if you don't do well then
it's your fault and so God is saying
don't don't bring your damned problems
to me bucko it's like if this isn't
working out for you it's because you're
just not doing it right you know you're
not into this properly you're not doing
well and also you're blending things
that shouldn't be blamed now there's an
interesting part of this so the the way
that the story sin lies at your
or was told it was told in the
metaphorical structure and sin was
something that was conceptualized as a
lustful predatory animal like a cat and
so it was prowling at Cain's door that's
the metaphor and the idea is that Cain
allows this thing in to have intercourse
with him so there's this participation
in like a sexualized merger and so
there's a there's an implication there
and the implication is not only is that
does sin at the door but Cain invites it
in and has a creative relationship like
an intimately creative relationship with
it now that's ridiculously smart because
that's what happens if people are
resentful because they're offerings that
were either second-rate or got rejected
you know one of the pathways is first
they get very very angry and their
countenance fall so they're resentful
and hostile and the next thing is you
know the little resentful fantasy start
to emerge and instead of thinking huh
that's not a very productive way to go
because it is like a door they think wow
let's just see where we can go with this
and like after five or six years of that
you're in a prime position to go shoot
up Dawson College you know you can go
very far down that rabbit hole and it's
it's clearly motivated by the rejection
of the fruits of your being by existence
that's how you're going to interpret it
so well and then so so Cain obviously
he's not happy with that response not in
the least because it says exactly the
opposite of what he would like it to say
you know first of all that it's his own
fault that he could do something about
it and then he doesn't get to blame
being and God
so Cain goes and has a chat with Abel
and it came came to pass when they were
in the field that Cain rose up against
Abel his brother and killed him well the
first story about real human beings in
the Bible is a murder
it's a fratricide and it's it's the it's
the antagonistic brothers one who is an
archetype of good that's Abel the others
who an archetype of evil and those
develop across time it's a it's an
echoing or a pre shadowing that's
the way of thinking about it a battle
between Christ and Satan because those
are more they're more purely archetypal
figures and much more fleshed out but
it's the earliest manifestation of that
idea the hostile brothers and what you
get it's so sophisticated because
basically what it says is that if you do
badly or you work hard either way and
God rejects your offerings and you
become angry and resentful the first
thing you're going to do is go after the
best thing you could possibly imagine
and do your best to wipe it out and you
might say well why would you do that
well there's a bunch of reasons well
first of all it would feel good second
you get revenge against God because of
course this is God's favorite so if you
can take him out of the equation it's
like that's a great deal
third the ideal against which you're
negatively contrasting yourself is now
gone because that's the problem with
having an ideal if you have an ideal
then you're unworthy and that's okay if
you think the ideal is attainable or
even if you can move towards it but if
all of a sudden the ideal is
unattainable and you're sort of cast
among the Damned the probability that
you're going to be able to view that
ideal as anything other than your enemy
is very low and so Cain kills him so
that's interesting because that that
really means that's the end of it for
Cain he's destroyed his own ideal well
how do you live then how do you live if
you've destroyed your own ideal you've
got nowhere to go
and so Cain is so angry that he's
willing to destroy his own ideal to
obtain revenge and that's 12 line story
right at the beginning of history and
that's the layout for the spirit of
humanity it says we became self
conscious our eyes opened we became self
conscious we recognized our
vulnerability in an attempt to overcome
that we started to work and sacrifice
but the problem with that is sometimes
that didn't work maybe because God was
feeling particularly arbitrary that day
or because we're kind of useless either
way when it doesn't work that's not good
because it's our only remaining defense
and so then what well then it's a choice
it's more it's more choice right there
between good and evil and that's all for
shadowed in the first story
so now I have one more thing to this
this took me a long time to figure out I
thought well what the hell is the
connection between the knowledge of good
and evil and nakedness and vulnerability
and an awareness and I thought okay
there's predators predation and there's
evil so the lion kills the default and
eats it it's rough that's a tragedy but
you capture an enemy and then you keep
them alive for three weeks in pain
before you kill them there's a lot more
there than tragedy that's malevolence
and then you might say well how is it
that you can come up with malevolence
and I would say as soon as you're self
conscious you can come up with
malevolence because if I know how I'm
vulnerable and I know that you're like
me all I have to do is figure out what
the worst possible thing would be for me
and then I can do it to you and so you
don't get the knowledge of self
conscious vulnerability without
instantly also obtaining the knowledge
of the difference between good and evil
and that's also another thing that
really distinguishes people because we
can do things that are so terrible but
they make any of the things that animals
do look positively forgivable so you
know that long without self
consciousness comes this tremendous
widening of the capacity for action from
just natural tragedy let's say this
natural life to this whole spectrum of
the ultimate and good and the ultimate
and evil and then as soon as that
happens the first thing we have is a
display of that in in dramatic form and
that's the Cain and Abel story now
interestingly enough and this is the
last thing that I'll tell you God
doesn't kill Cain we can talk about why
that is later but Cain has children and
and and Cain's descendants I think three
generations down so if you kill one
Akane's sons he kills seven of you they
kill seven of you and if you kill one of
Cain's grandchildren then they kill 49
of you and then and so forth until you
get to this guy named tubal Cain who's
either the grandson or the
great-grandson I don't remember which
and
in tradition he's the first person who
makes weapons of war so there's this
idea that the sacrifice fails and that
produces this descent into murderous
resentment and then that can amplify
across the culture and possess more and
more people until what happens is it
finally erupts in full full-scale war
and that's more than territoriality
rights more than a territorial dispute
because you can understand territorial
disputes this is territorial dispute
with malevolence and you know that's
something that you that doesn't need any
explanation we everyone understands what
that is